<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God's king the people's blessing. A sermon preached on the day of thanksgiving for peace, at St. Ann's Church in Dungannon, in the diocese of Armagh. / By Edm. Arwaker, rector of Drumglass, and chaplain to his grace the Duke of Ormond.</title>
            <author>Arwaker, Edmund</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170385</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504697</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171592</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171592)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2577:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God's king the people's blessing. A sermon preached on the day of thanksgiving for peace, at St. Ann's Church in Dungannon, in the diocese of Armagh. / By Edm. Arwaker, rector of Drumglass, and chaplain to his grace the Duke of Ormond.</title>
                  <author>Arwaker, Edmund</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Ray, and are to be Sold at his Shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XC VIII [1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 2nd, IX, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Thanksgiving sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171592:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>God's King the People's Bleſſing.</hi> A SERMON Preached on the Day of THANKSGIVING FOR PEACE, At St. <hi>Ann</hi>'s Church in <hi>Dungannon,</hi> In the Dioceſs of <hi>ARMAGH.</hi> By <hi>EDM. ARWAKER,</hi> Rector of <hi>Drumglaſs,</hi> and Chaplain to his Grace the DUKE of <hi>ORMOND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DUBLIN:</hi> Printed by <hi>Joſeph Ray,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop in <hi>Skinner-Row,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Tholſel.</hi> M DC XC VIII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171592:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:171592:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To His GRACE MICHAEL Lord Archbiſhop of</hi> Armagh, <hi>Primate and Metropolitan of all</hi> Ireland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Can make no Apology to the Publick, for ſending this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe abroad; nor to Your Grace, for its appearing under Your Patronage; but that I believe the Occaſion of it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently Agreeable and Satisfactory to Both, to gain Your Approbation of the Deſign: For the Sincerity whereof, I am induced to hope You will Accept the Performance, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don its Imperfections.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, His Majeſty has done ſo Great Things for our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that He needs not the Help of any Weak Endeavours to Support His Intereſt, or Endear His Perſon and Government to their Inhabitants; Yet ſince He who was above all Praiſe of Men, did vouchſafe to Accept it from the Mouth of Babes and Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, to ſtill the Enemy and Avenger; Why may not as mean an Orator prove Serviceable to put to ſilence the Ignorance of Fooliſh Men, who have ſaid of our Soveraign, as thoſe in the Parable, of their King, <hi>We will not have this Man to Reign over us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hope of ſuch Good Succeſs, and ſome little Good Liking that my Hearers diſcovered to this Sermon, after its Delivery from the Pulpit, encouraged me to venture it to the Preſs: And that Preſumption drew me into a Greater, to ſhelter it under Your Graces Name.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171592:3"/>
            <p>But, Since Men that fly to Altars for Sanctuary, ought to bring Offerings thither with them; I humbly beg leave to Aſſure Your Grace, That in this Dedication, I aim no leſs at an Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment for Your paſt Favour, in Collating me to a Conſiderable Benefice, than at Your Future Countenance and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And I eſteem my ſelf under the Greater Obligation to Your Goodneſs, that notwithſtanding Your Grace's Extraordinary Care to provide an Able and Deſerving Clergy for Your Dioceſs, You have however Admitted me into that Learned and Reverend Society; my Unworthineſs of which, makes me ſeem to my ſelf like <hi>Saul</hi> among the Prophets.</p>
            <p>Might I be Improved by the Advantage of ſuch Excellent Converſation, to Propheſie to the Edifying of the People whom I have in Charge, I ſhou'd be Happy in ſeveral reſpects: But in none more, than in making Your Grace, by that means, the Beſt Return within my Power, for all Your Benefits; Since no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo pleaſing to You in Your Clergie, as the Diligent and Exact Performance of their Duty on their Cures.</p>
            <p>For the Continuance whereof, May Your Grace live long, to Oblige and Encourage them to it: And as You have Honourably Born, and Faithfully Diſcharged, the Higheſt Offices in our Church and State; So may You, when You ſhall be taken from this World, Arrive at a Proportionable Degree of Glory in the Coeleſtial Hierarchy, to receive Above, the Reward of all the Good You bave done Below; and particularly to,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt Obliged, and moſt Dutiful Son and Servant, <hi>EDM. ARWAKER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171592:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 CHRON. IX. 8.</bibl> Bleſſed be the Lord thy God, which delighted in thee, to ſet thee on his Throne, to be King for the Lord thy God: Becauſe thy God loved Iſrael to Eſtabliſh them for ever, therefore made he thee King over them, to do Judgment and Juſtice.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SO Great, ſo Valuable is the Bleſſing which we this Day Celebrate, even the Bleſſing of Peace in all our Lands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29. 10. So long has it been Want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Deſired, ſo Earneſtly has it been Purſu'd and Sought, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 14. And at laſt ſo happily Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and Settled, that we can never ſufficiently Adore the Goodneſs of our God, the Author, nor enough Applaud the Gonduct of our King, the Inſtrument of its Joyful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration.</p>
            <p>But tho' our Gratitude cannot reach the Inacceſſible Height of this Obligation, yet ſhou'd we fail in our Juſt Endeavours to Acknowledge it, the Queen of the South wou'd riſe up in Judgment with us, and condemn us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 42. For ſhe was drawn from the uttermoſt parts of the Earth, to hear the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and to admire the great and wonderful Effects of it, not only in his Proverbs and Anſwers, but in the Grandeur and Magnificence of his Court, and in the Plenty and Tranquility of his Kingdom, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 4, 5. And behold! thro' the tender Mercy of our God, if not a Greater, yet one little leſs than <hi>Solomon</hi> is among us; a Prince by whoſe Excellent Management our Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are brought to reſemble <hi>Iſraels,</hi> in his Days, when every man dwelt ſafely under his Vine, and under his Fig-Tree, from <hi>Dan</hi> even to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4. 15.</p>
            <p>Since then our King, like <hi>Solomon,</hi> has Peace on all ſides
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171592:4"/> round about him, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4. 24. Since the Lord has given him Reſt and Safety from the Fatigues and Dangers of a Tedious War; and ſince we, not only in our Juſt Concern for Him, but through His Care of us, partake of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Benefit; ſo that there is neither Adverſary, nor Evil Occurrent, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 5. 4. No Complaining in our Streets, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. 14. but the Voice of Joy and Gladneſs: If the People are happy, who are in ſuch a caſe; if they are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed who have the Lord for their God, to Eſtabliſh their Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, by giving them ſo Excellent a Prince; We ought cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to be Senſible of our Happineſs, and Grateful for it.</p>
            <p>And how can we better render, either to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s, or to God the things that are Gods? <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 21. How more ſuitably extol the Merits of our King, or the Goodneſs of the King of Kings in giving him to us, than in the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi>'s Congratulatory Complement to <hi>Solomon,</hi> when ſhe found how much the Fame ſhe had heard, was inferiour to the Truth of his Acts, and of his Wiſdom, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9. 5, 6. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord thy God?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which Words afford three things to our Obſervation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The certain Evidence of God's Favour and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his People, in placing a Good King over them: <hi>Becauſe thy God loved Iſrael, to Eſtabliſh them for ever, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made he thee King over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Excellent Qualifications of the Prince whom God makes choice of to convey Bleſſings to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; implied in theſe words, <hi>Which delighted in thee, to ſet thee on his Throne, to be King for the Lord thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Grateful Acknowledgements due from Gods People, both to God and the King; for the Unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Benefits of the One's Care and Kindneſs, in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Advantages of the Other's Government; which oblige them to ſay, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171592:4"/>
            <q>That God's Placing a Good King over his People, is a certain Evidence of his Favour towards them.</q>
            <p>The Bleſſing of leading a quiet and peaceable Life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty, is by St. <hi>Paul</hi> aſcribed to the Juſt Adminiſtration of the Regal Power; wherefore he exhorts <hi>that Prayers, Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks, be made for Kings, and all that are in Authority,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 1, 2. that they may be Good, in order to make their Subjects Happy. And indeed, the General Welfare of a Nation depends ſo much upon the Temper of its Governours, that God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares he gave <hi>Iſrael</hi> a King in his Anger, when he placed <hi>Saul</hi> on the Throne, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 11. And he threatens it as a Puniſhment for their not fearing him, that they ſhou'd be deprived of the Benefits they enjoyed under the happy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of their better Princes; and ſay, We have no Kings, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10. 3. And the ſeverity of this Curſe will appear from the Obſervation, That <hi>when there was no King in Iſrael, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one did that which was right in his own Eyes,</hi> Judg. 17. 6. And what is to be expected but Confuſion in that State, where every diſtemper'd Humour is the Rule for diſorder'd Actions? Where there is no Superiour Power to controul the Unruly Wills of Men, ſway'd by their Luſts and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions?</p>
            <p>But the Advantages of a <hi>Good King</hi> are not ſo well diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the Inconveniencies of having <hi>No King,</hi> as from the Miſeries which a People ſuffers under an <hi>Evil King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Iſrael</hi> had deſired a King, and the Prophet thus deſcribed the manner of the King that ſhould Reign over them; That <hi>he wou'd take their Sons and appoint them for himſelf, for his Chariots, and to be his Horſemen, and ſome ſhou'd run before his Chariots; And that he would appoint him Captains over Thouſands, and Captains over Fifties, and ſet them to Ear his Ground, and to Reap his Harveſt, and to make his Inſtruments of War, and Inſtruments of his Chariots: And that he would make their Daughters to be Confectionaries, and</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171592:5"/> 
               <hi>Cooks, and Bakers: And that he wou'd,</hi> with an Arbitrary Injuſtice, <hi>take their Fields, and their Vineyards, and their Olive-yards, and diſpoſe of them to his Servants:</hi> And that he would <hi>take their Men-ſervants, and their goodlieſt young Men, and their Aſſes, and put them to his work; nay, and make themſelves his Servants,</hi> 1 Sam. 8. 11. <hi>to</hi> 18. Wou'd they not have Reaſon to cry out in that day, becauſe of ſuch a King; and conclude that inſtead of a <hi>Nurſing Father,</hi> Iſa. 49. 23. God had given them a <hi>Devouring Lion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor wou'd they be Sufferers only from the Tyranny and Injuſtice of their King; his Imprudence, Intemperance, Irreſolution, or Impiety, would be as injurious to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> denounces a <hi>Wo to that Land whoſe King is a Child,</hi> Eccleſ. 10. 6. That is, Not ſo much in Years, as in Underſtanding; whoſe Ignorance how to Govern, deſtroys his People by Male-Adminiſtration: For even a <hi>Child,</hi> in reſpect of years, if <hi>Wiſe,</hi> is <hi>better than an Old and Fooliſh King, that will not be admoniſhed,</hi> Eccleſ. 4. 13. That being grown old and hardned in his Folly, is Irreclaimable by Reproof, and paſt all Hope and Expectation of Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Advice.</p>
            <p>How miſerable muſt a People be under ſuch a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who, tho' ignorant how to Rule them, will not however be Adviſed, but is obſtinately wedded to his own Opinion, and rejects that Safety which is in the multitude of Counſellors? <hi>Prov.</hi> 11. 14. Thus, Not the green Years, but Imprudence of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> in making him ſlight the Counſel of thoſe Old Men that ſtood before <hi>Solomon</hi> his Father, and prefer the Advice of others, whoſe want of Judgment and Experience render'd them unfit to be conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; made <hi>Iſrael</hi> caſt off his Government, and Rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 8. and 19. And he juſtly deſerved the Ignominious Character which the Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> gives him, <hi>That he was the Fooliſhneſs of the People, and one that had no Underſtanding; ſince he turned away the People through his giddy and inconſiderate Counſel,</hi> Ecclus. 47.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171592:5"/> 23. Which ſufficiently declares God's ſevere Diſpleaſure againſt <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when he threatens that he <hi>will take away from them the Prudent, the Ancient, and the Counſellour, and give Children to be their Princes, and Babes to Rule over them,</hi> Iſa. 3. 2, 3, 4. For the conſequence will be Oppreſſion, Rapine, Ruine and Deſtruction, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5, 8. And how ſad and calamitous muſt the condition of a People be, when their Domeſtick Jars weaken and expoſe them to Foreign Outrage and Inſults? How eaſily ſhall they be Overcome and made a Prey, when the ſame want of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in their Ruler, which hinder'd him from keeping them in Peace, will not let him with good Advice make War? <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 18.</p>
            <p>Nor is a People in more danger from the Imprudence, than from the Intemperance of a Prince, whether in reſpect of Exceſs as to Meat and Drink, or Immoderation in other Appetites. Misfortune attends that Land, <hi>whoſe Princes eat in a Morning, for Drunkenneſs and not for Strength,</hi> Eccleſ. 10. 16, 17. For when <hi>Kings drink Wine, and Princes ſtrong Drink, they forget the Law, and pervert the Judgment of the Afflicted,</hi> Prov. 31. 4, 5. They incapacitate themſelves to Govern by Law or Reaſon, and ſo cloud their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that it cannot diſcern what is Juſt and Equitable. And when Reaſon is ſo weakned, Paſſion will quickly be predominant; and then as he that cannot rule his Spirit, will be as a City that is broken down, and without Walls, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25. 28. So he will break down all the Fences of Law and Juſtice, of Clemency and Moderation, and will run into all the Violence and Outrage, to which his Ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd and Miſguided Will inclines him; will be like a Lion in his Houſe, and Frantick among his Servants, <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 4. 30. And as when his Belly is his God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 19. he will ſacrifice the Revenues of his Kingdom to his Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite; ſo when his Will is his Law, he will ſubject the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Properties of his People to its Determinations.</p>
            <p>But neither Imprudence nor Intemperance make a Prince
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171592:6"/> more pernicious to his People than Irreſolution and want of Courage, without which they cannot long continue in Peace, nor ſhall be Victorious in War. He whoſe ſtrength is ſo ſmall, that he faints in the day of Adverſity, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 10. and turns himſelf back in the day of Battel, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 9. leaves his Realms Defenceleſs, and his People without Protection. He that has not Courage enough to do Valiantly, and to play the Man for his People, and the Cities of his God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 12. will leave them like Sheep without a Shepherd, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. 16. to glut the Sword and Fury of their Enemies, to be ſpoiled and ſlaughtered by them. For when he that ſhou'd lead them on, is the firſt whoſe Heart faints, and ſeeks for Safety rather in Flight than Forwardneſs, how ſhall they but follow his Example, and turn their Backs to the Smiters? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50. 6.</p>
            <p>Courage is ſo neceſſary a Qualification for a King, for the Defence and Safety of his Subjects, that we find when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God rais'd up a Deliverer for his People, he inſpir'd him with an extraordinary Valour, <hi>Taught his hand to war, and his fingers to fight,</hi> Pſal. 144. 1. <hi>The time would fail me to tell of Gideon, and of Barak, of Sampſon and of Jephthah, who through Faith</hi> were endued with that Courage by which <hi>they ſubdued Kingdoms, eſcaped the edge of the Sword, waxed valiant in Fight, and turned to flight the Armies of the Aliens,</hi> Heb. 11. 32, 33, 34. And the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were ſo ſenſible of the evil conſequences of wanting a King to go out before them, and fight their Battels, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 20. that they ſtill perſiſted to deſire one for that reaſon, notwithſtanding all the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of it, repreſented to them by <hi>Samuel,</hi> to divert them from that Requeſt.</p>
            <p>And tho' <hi>Saul</hi> proved as great a Scourge to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the Prophet had fore-told he would, yet ſince <hi>from the Blood of the Slain, and from the Fat of the Mighty, the Sword of Saul returned not empty; David</hi> reckoned it as juſt a reaſon for the Daughters of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to weep over him, as his <hi>Cloathing them in Scarlet, and putting Ornaments of Gold on their Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel;</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171592:6"/> and he knew that the occaſion of their Sorrow would make the <hi>Daughters of the Philiſtines rejoyce and triumph,</hi> to find the <hi>Mighty fallen,</hi> by whom <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtood, and <hi>the Shield of Saul,</hi> which was his Peoples Shelter, <hi>vilely caſt away,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 19. to the end. But the <hi>Weapons of War</hi> were not wholly periſhed, while <hi>David</hi> yet ſurvived, and ſucceeded in the Kingdom; ſince 'tis part of his Character, <hi>That he play'd with Lions as with Kids, and with Bears as it had been Lambs; that he ſlew a Giant when he was yet but young, and took away the reproach from the People, whn he lifted up his hand with the Stone in the Sling, and beat down the boaſting of Goliah,</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus. 47. 2, 3. So great a Man of War he was, ſo mighty valiant, that he could as well put to flight the Enemies that Invaded <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> as the Evil Spirit that diſturbed <hi>Saul;</hi> and compoſe the Troubles in the heart of his Country, as the Diſquiets in the Breaſt of his King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 18, 23.</p>
            <p>But the Safety and Honour which his Country found in the great Effects of his Invincible Courage, was afterwards often loſt and laid in the duſt, by the want of that Vertue in many of his Succeſſors: Which may ſuffice to ſhew how fatal this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in a Prince is to his People.</p>
            <p>But in no Miſcarriage of the King, is the Misfortune of his People ſo great, as in his Impiety and Diſregard of God; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Grievances of his Evil Reign, and the Miſchiefs they ſuffer from himſelf; the Wickedneſs of a King brings Afflictions from Heaven upon his People, in that his Example generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails with them to deſerve them.</p>
            <p>Thus when <hi>Rehoboam</hi> forſook the Law of the Lord, all <hi>Iſrael</hi> did ſo with him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 1. And tho' at the Preaching of <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiah,</hi> they Repented, and were delivered from Deſtruction, yet were they not exempt from Spoil; For <hi>Shiſhak</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> came up againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and took away the Treaſures of the Lord's Houſe, as well as of the King's, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. and the People were made his Servants, that they might know Gods Service better, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Wickedneſs provoked God to ſhut up the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of Heaven, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17. 1. and to with-hold from <hi>Iſrael</hi> the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171592:7"/> common Mercies of Dew and Rain, which he uſually beſtows alike on the Juſt and Unjuſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 45. ſo that there was a ſore Famine in <hi>Samaria,</hi> 1 King. 18. 2. and the People wanted their dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bread, becauſe their King had forſaken Him, who alone fills all things living with Plenteouſneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 16.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Jehoram</hi>'s working that which was Evil in the Eyes of the Lord, cauſed the Revolt of the <hi>Edomites</hi> and <hi>Libnah,</hi> not only from under his hand, but the hand of <hi>Judah:</hi> And 'tis aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for the reaſon of this Defection, <hi>Becauſe he had forſaken the Lord God of his Fathers.</hi> For which Impiety of his, his People are threatned with a Plague, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 10, 14. To die an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely Death, for the Irregularities of his Life.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Ahaz</hi>'s wicked Reign expoſed his People as well as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to the hand of the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> who not only ſmote him, but carried away a great multitude of his Subjects Captives to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. 5. And afterwards he was delivered into the hands of the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who ſmote him with a great ſlaughter, ſo that there were ſlain in <hi>Judah</hi> in one day 120000, which were all valiant Men; and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> carried away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to <hi>Samaria</hi> 200000 Women, Sons, and Daughters, with much Spoil, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6, 8. And as if this had not been enough, the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> alſo invaded, and took no leſs than ſix of the Cities of <hi>Judah, whom the Lord brought low becauſe of Ahaz; for he made Judah Naked, and tranſgreſſed ſore againſt the Lord,</hi> V. 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Since then the Sin of an Evil King is often the Reproach and Ruine of his People, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 34. How great a Bleſſing is a good King to his Subjects, becauſe he not only frees them from this Misfortune, but is Inſtrumental to procure and promote their Happineſs? Which occaſioned that ſaying of the Pſalmiſt, of ſuch a one, <hi>Thou haſt ſet him to be Bleſſings for ever,</hi> Pſal. 21. 6. for ſo 'tis in the Original; ſignifying that a Good King is the means of conveying many Bleſſings to his People. And this Truth has been proved by a <hi>Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> Heb. 12. 1. How did <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> enjoy the Benefit of <hi>Aſa</hi>'s Piety? The firſt ten years of his Reign <hi>the Land was quiet,</hi> 2 Chron. 14. 1. and he had no War, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord had given him reſt,</hi> Verſ. 6. <hi>ſo that the People built</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171592:7"/> 
               <hi>and proſpered,</hi> Verſ. 7. And when <hi>Zerah</hi> the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> came to diſturb their Peace, he did it to the Ruine of his own, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. for the Men of <hi>Judah overthrew and ſpoiled him,</hi> Verſ. 13. and had <hi>no War unto the five and thirtieth year of the Reign of Aſa,</hi> Chap. 15. 19. This Tranquility his People had, becauſe he <hi>did that which was good and right in the Eyes of the Lord his God,</hi> 2 Chron. 14. 2. And they, after his Example, had <hi>entred into a Covenant to ſeek the Lord God of their Fathers;</hi> which as they had <hi>ſworn with all their heart,</hi> they <hi>performed with their whole deſire.</hi> Chap. 15. 15. And <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſucceeding to his Father's Piety, as well as to his Throne, continues his Peoples happineſs. The Kingdom was not only ſtabliſhed in his hand, ſo that he had <hi>Riches and Honour in abundance,</hi> 2 Chron. 17. 5. but <hi>the fear of the Lord fell upon all the Kingdoms of the Lands that were round about Judah, ſo that they made no War againſt Jehoſaphat,</hi> Verſ. 10.</p>
            <p>And when afterwards the Children of <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> came againſt him to Battel, they were deſtroyed; but his People re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with Joy; and his Realm was quiet, <hi>becauſe the Lord had given him reſt,</hi> 2 Chron. 20. 30. So certain it is, that <hi>when a Mans Ways pleaſe the Lord, he maketh even his Enemies to be at Peace with him,</hi> Prov. 16. 7.</p>
            <p>For this are Good Kings called, <hi>The Breath of their Peoples No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils,</hi> Lam. 4. 20. who live <hi>Safe</hi> under their <hi>Shadow,</hi> and enjoy Peace and Proſperity by their means. And ſince it is by God that <hi>Kings Reign,</hi> Prov. 8. 15. it muſt needs be an Evidence of his ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Favour to that People over whom he places a Good King, whoſe Excellent Qualifications eſtabliſh their Felicity, and whoſe Great Example teaches them the Practice of that Righteouſneſs which exalts a Nation, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 34.</p>
            <p>Since then <hi>Solomon</hi> had not only brought Plenty to his People, in making Silver as common at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> as the Stones, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 27. but Peace and Splendor too; the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> might very reaſonable conclude, that, <hi>Becauſe God loved Iſrael, to Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them for ever, therefore he made him King over them.</hi> And as his love to <hi>Iſrael</hi> made him bleſs them with ſo Good a King; ſo his taking a delight in <hi>Solomon,</hi> induced him to make Choice
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171592:8"/> of him, <hi>to ſet him upon his Throne, to be King for the Lord his God;</hi> ſince he found in him thoſe Excellencies and Perfections which endear a King to God, and render him a Bleſſing to his People. For the Vertues of Juſtice, Prudence, Temperance, Fortitude and Piety, (the want of which in a King, I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewn to be of pernicious conſequence to his Subjects) were ſo ſignally Eminent in <hi>Solomon,</hi> that his People could not deſire a more Accompliſh'd Soveraign to compleat their Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Juſtice, which is a conſtant and perpetual Will to render every Man his Right, or rather a habit of ſo doing upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, was the Rule of all <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Adminiſtrations. This was <hi>Judah</hi>'s and <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Security in the Poſſeſſion of their Rights and Properties, and gave every Man a ſafe Enjoyment of his own Vine, and his own Figtree, all the Days of that Righteous King. And this could not but be well-pleaſing to God, as giving Man a near Reſemblance of himſelf, who <hi>is Righteous in all his Ways,</hi> Pſal. 145. 17. And being advantagious to his People, in keeping them from Injuries and Oppreſſion, and ſecuring them in the Poſſeſſion of thoſe Acquiſts to which they had juſt Right and Title. Thus, <hi>A Divine Sentence is in the Lips of the King, when his Mouth tranſgreſſeth not in Judgment,</hi> Prov. 16. 10. and by it he <hi>eſtabliſheth the Land,</hi> Prov. 29. 4.</p>
            <p>But to do Impartial Juſtice, requires a Solid Prudence; which being a True Habit of Acting with Reaſon, in reſpect of thoſe things that concern the well or ill being of Men, muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be a Requiſite Qualification for Kings, on whoſe Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Happineſs or Miſery of their Realms muſt neceſſarily depend.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration of this, prevailed with <hi>Solomon,</hi> when God left it to his Option to ask what he ſhould give him, to deſire <hi>an Underſtanding Heart to judge his People, that he might diſcern between Good and Bad,</hi> 1 King. 3. 9. Which Choice, was an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he was in great meaſure endued already with what he ſo judiciouſly deſired: And God was ſo well pleaſed with his Petition, that he not only gave him what he asked, but an Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus of Riches and Honour, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171592:8"/>
            <p>Now how ſignal his Prudence was, and how great the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits thereof, appears from his Celebrated Deciſion between the Harlots, who contended for the living Child, ver. 27. Which proves it as much the Happineſs of a People, as the Honour of a King, that he ſhou'd be able to ſearch out a matter, by ſo nice a Scrutiny, <hi>Pro.</hi> 25. 2. And ſince the Wiſdom of God was in him to do Judgment, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 3. 28. it muſt needs pleaſe him to ſee the Stream retain the Pureneſs of its Fountain, and he wou'd Love him for this, as much as all <hi>Iſrael</hi> Feared him. Nor did <hi>Solomon</hi> permit his Juſtice to be perverted, or his Prudence baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled, by any manner of Intemperance, but as thoſe Virtues were his Peoples Safeguard againſt Injuries and Outrages from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo his Temperance was their Defence againſt all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and Severity from himſelf. But, when magnified in the nobleſt part and demonſtration of it, Clemency; it free'd them from the Juſt Puniſhments they had deſerved, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked him to inflict on them, by their Crimes.</p>
            <p>This was evident in his dealing with <hi>Adonijah,</hi> whom tho' he had ſet up a Title to the Crown, he pardon'd; and aſſured that <hi>if he wou'd ſhew himſelf a worthy man, there ſhou'd not an hair of his Head fall to the earth,</hi> 1 King. 1. 52.</p>
            <p>Nor was it leſs viſible in his proceedings with <hi>Abiathar,</hi> who promoted the Uſurpation; for tho' the King declared him worthy of Death, yet he contented himſelf with depoſing him from the Prieſthood, and confining him to his Houſe at <hi>Anathoth,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 26. Thus by his ſlowneſs to Anger, did he render himſelf better than by all his Might; and greater in Ruling his Spirit, than in the Government of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Pro. 16. 32. and as it was his Glory, ſo it prov'd his Peoples Safety; and God, <hi>who his is ſlow to Anger and of great Goodneſs,</hi> cou'd not but be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with Qualities ſo reſembling his own, and chuſe him for the Repreſentative of his Power, as fitteſt to Rule Others, who had ſo great a Government over Himſelf.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> were thus obliged to their King for their Domeſtick Eaſe and Enjoyments, they were no leſs indebted to him for their Protection from Foreign Ravages and Incurſions,</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:171592:9"/>
            <p>Fortitude, which is a Mediocrity between Fear and Confidence, was ſo eminent in <hi>Solomon,</hi> that it left him no Famous Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of exerting it, more than in the Methods which took the occaſion from him. It led him to ſtrengthen himſelf with all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Proviſions of War; at Land, with a powerful Army, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 1. 14. By Sea, with a ſufficient Fleet, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 26. Which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied him with Gold from <hi>Ophir,</hi> to ſupport the charge of both, ver. 28.</p>
            <p>So that he kept his People in Peace Fourty Years, a Bleſſing which needs no other recommendation than the Terrors and Calamities of War.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their young men were not ſlain with the Sword, nor their Cities waſted;</hi> there was <hi>no deſolation in their Fields, nor complaining in their Streets; but Judah and Iſrael</hi> were <hi>many, as the ſand which is by the Sea in multitude, eating and drinking, and making merry;</hi> 2. King. 4. 20. There was no one durſt attempt to diſturb or trouble them, but their Tranquillity was firm and unſhaken as the Reſolution of their King; who cou'd not have manifeſted his Fortitude ſo much in <hi>ſubduing Enemies,</hi> as he did in <hi>prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his having Enemies to ſubdue;</hi> and keeping his People in ſo perfect a Peace, that it was preferable to the greateſt Victories. And as God, who was always loving to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and deſirous of their Eſtabliſhment, had reaſon to be delighted with that Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, which ſo highly contributed to it; and to place the Owner of it on his Throne, <hi>to be King for the Lord his God;</hi> ſo he found in <hi>Solomon</hi> another Vertue, which crowned the reſt, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them more Amiable and Advantageous; and that was Piety, or the Love and Fear of God. I ſhall not trouble you with many Inſtances of this, but let one ſuffice for all, I mean that Everlaſting Monument thereof, the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Which Work, as it received Gods Extraordinary Approbation, when it was finiſhed, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. 1, 2, 3. So it remains upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, in ſacred Writ, as an Evidence of its Founders Zeal and Reverence for his Worſhip, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 47.</p>
            <p>And ſince the concurrence of theſe Vertues in a King, tend to Compleat and Eſtabliſh the Proſperity of his People; it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171592:9"/> certain, that God, by giving any Nation a Prince in whom they are Eminently Viſible and United, does thereby give the moſt convincing Evidence of his Favour and Affection towards them, and of his being highly delighted in the Perſon who is ſo much after his own Heart, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 14. So qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be his Vicegerent. And this certainly requires the moſt Extenſive Gratitude and Acknowledgments of that People, for whom God makes ſuch a happy Choice, in admiring his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which deſign'd, and applauding their Soveraigns Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which concur with it, to effect their Eſtabliſhment and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity: That having a King like <hi>Solomon,</hi> they ſhou'd ſay as much to him, as the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> to that Great and Glorious Monarch, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And if ever People had reaſon to Adreſs their God, or their King, on ſuch an account, and in ſuch a ſtyle; We certainly of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> lie under as great, and as many Obligations to Both.</p>
            <p>For our Almighty Soveraign Above, has bleſt us with a King Below, ſufficiently furniſh'd and inrich'd with all thoſe Vertues that are requiſite to make us as happy a People as we can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be in the largeſt extent of our own Wiſhes.</p>
            <p>So Juſt he has proved in the Adminiſtration of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he has not only eſchew'd the Evil of incroaching on our Liberties and Properties, but he has done the Good of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing us in thoſe Rights of Engliſhmen, with which all who are truly ſuch, ſhou'd as obſtinately refuſe to part, as <hi>Naboth</hi> with his Vineyard, ſince we have the ſame reaſon to alledg, That <hi>they are the Inheritance of our Fathers,</hi> 1 King. 21. 3. But ſo careful our Soveraign has been to oppoſe the Fence of our Ancient Laws and Priviledges againſt all Incroachments from Himſelf as well as Others, that nothing has been laid upon us in all his Reign, to which we have not firſt conſented by our <hi>Repreſentatives.</hi> Nor cou'd we fear he ſhou'd offer any Violence to our Laws, who came to us on purpoſe to Maintain them, when he ſaw an Arbitrary Power ready to throw down that hedg, and lay us open to its Devaſtations.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:171592:10"/>
            <p>This quick and happy foreſight of the Storm that then was gathering, and ready to diſcharge its fury on us; to Cruſh us with the weight of Lawleſs Power, and Poyſon us with the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom of Popiſh Principles; and the Timely as well as Happy Prevention of thoſe Calamities, have ſufficiently magnified his Prudence; ſo that whether we conſider him on the Throne, ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Regal Scepter, or in the Camp, weilding the Martial Sword, we muſt confeſs he has <hi>guided us by the Skillfulneſs of his Hands,</hi> Pſ. 78. 72.</p>
            <p>And as his Wiſdom has made us Safe, ſo his Great Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Moderation (Sufficiently known to all men, <hi>Phil.</hi> 45. even to his greateſt Enemies) has rendred us Eaſy too, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Government: No Indulgence either to his Palate, or his Paſſion, has diſturbed the Evenneſs of his Temper.</p>
            <p>Tho he has often been provoked to be Vindictive, by horrid Deſigns of Barbarous Aſſaſſinations, yet he has ſhown as little Inclination to Revenge, as Fear; and has ſpared to ſhed Their Blood, whoſe Thirſt was Inſatiable after His.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhou'd it ſeem ſtrange he ſhou'd be ſo tender of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Lives, for whoſe Safety he has frequently expoſed his Own; and that in the greateſt Inſtances of an Unparallell'd Fortitude; in Doing and in Suffering things almoſt incredible.</p>
            <p>Perhaps never any King made his way ſo often thro' the Sea, even among thoſe who claim the Soveraignty and Dominion of it; and that not only in Calm and Temperate Weather, when the Winds were Still, and the Ocean Smooth; but even when Tempeſts Roard aloud, and the Waves Raged horribly: Nay when they were Congealed to Rocks of Ice, by the Coldneſs of the Climate and the Seaſon.</p>
            <p>Yet as he engaged in theſe Difficulties, with an Undaunted Conſtancy and Reſolution, ſo he under went them all with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Patience, and an Unwearied Perſeverance: Tho' he knew he was to run theſe Hazards only in purſuit of Greater, and went to expoſe his Life to an Hoſt of Enemies; among whom, there neither wanted ſome who had Gallantry enough to attack it Bravely and with Vigor; nor others, whoſe Malice led them to attempt it Baſely by Aſſaſſination.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:171592:10"/>
            <p>His Generous Courage prompted him to preſs with greateſt Eagerneſs, where he ſaw the moſt imminent Danger in his way: So that he was in Labours abundant, and in Deaths oft; in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils in the City, and in Perils on the Sea; in Wearineſs and Painfulneſs, in Watchings and in Cold, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23, 26, 27. And all this he endured for us, and for our Eſtabliſhment; to perfect which, he has added Piety to his other Qualifications; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt as much Fear and Reverence of God, as Slight and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Dangers. His Precepts and Example have all along contributed to bring Religion into Vogue and Countenance; and to make us rather Sincere in the Practice, than Noiſy in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it; that we might reap the Fruit of Righteouſneſs, dwell in a Peaceable Habitation, and in quiet Reſting Places, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 17, 18. And that he might as happily Compleat, as he gloriouſly Undertook the Reſtoration of our Peace.</p>
            <p>And this, Thanks be to the God of Peace, he hath Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and Settled upon ſuch a Foundation as may by the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the ſame Power, prove a firm and laſting Tranquility to <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now ſince War is ceaſed in moſt part of the World, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. 9. ſo that <hi>Nation doth not lift up a Sword againſt Nation,</hi> but inſtead of Military Diſcipline, make Agriculture their Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>break their Swords into Plowſhares, and their Spears into Pruning-Hooks,</hi> Mic. 4. 3. Will not this tend to Wealth and Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? <hi>Shall not our Paſtures be cloathed with Flocks, our Valleys co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Corn?</hi> And while we eat in ſafety the Fruits of our Labours, ſhall we not <hi>ſhout for joy, and ſing? Pſal.</hi> 65. 13. And what Songs will ſo well become us, as Songs of Praiſe and Thankſgiving to our God, who by giving us ſo excellent a King, does build our <hi>Jeruſalem, ſtrengthen the Bars of her Gates, bleſs her Children within her, make Peace within her Borders, and fill her with the fineſt of the Wheat?</hi> Pſal. 147. 13, 14.</p>
            <p>And if we deſire ſtill to ſee <hi>Peace within her Walls, and Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs within her Palaces,</hi> Pſal. 122. 72. let us <hi>walk in the Name of the Lord our God for ever,</hi> Mic. 4. 5. <hi>Offer Sacrifices of ſweet ſavour</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:171592:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>unto him,</hi> and <hi>pray for the Life of the King,</hi> Ezra 6. 10. That he may live to <hi>Rectifie Corruptions and Abuſes, effectually to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Prophaneſs and Immorality, and employ his Thoughts in Advancing the Happineſs and Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">King's Speech to Parliament.</note> 
               <hi>Eſtate of all his Kingdoms; that he may ſo preſerve our Laws and Liberties Entire, and leave them ſo to Poſterity;</hi> that nothing may be left for his Succeſſors to do, but that which hath been already done, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2. 12. to continue them as they find them.</p>
            <p>And let our Gratitude to him, who next to God has been the happy Inſtrument of conveying theſe Bleſſings to us, make us ſo quiet and peaceable under his Government, that he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Pains he has taken for us, and be a Sharer in the Benefits that accrue to us by them. And let no Factious Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents be diſpleas'd with him, in whom 'tis Evident God De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, to ſet him on his Throne; and whom, becauſe he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us, he made King over us, to Eſtabliſh us.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe him therefore to continue the Mercy to us, in giving our Defender a long and proſperous Reign; that tho' we inceſſantly Commemorate with Thanks the Bleſſing of this Day, we may never in our time have a Second Occaſion of Thankſgiving for the Concluſion of a General Peace. <hi>Which God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:171592:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
